Hello, everyone. Welcome back to English
Pod. My name is Marco and I'm Erica and today
we're going to be going to one of the
least favorite places of many, many people.
So it must be the dentist.
Exactly. That place where you
have to go every six months,
but you probably don't go.
You probably don't.
I know I don't go every six months.
So yeah, we're going to be going to the
dentist and of course we're going to be looking
at a lot of great vocabulary related to
teeth and all that crazy stuff dentists do.
Yes, and we'll also learn
some really interesting phrases.
So Marco, let's get started
with our vocabulary preview.
Very vocabulary preview. Okay, and
vocabulary preview today. We have two words.
Let's take a look at the first one.
Toothache. Toothache. Toothache. Toothache.
Okay, so we've seen before this ending
ache, right? Right. It means it hurts.
Exactly. So again, a toothache would
be a hurting tooth. A hurting tooth. Yes.
We can also say stomach ache, headache.
Yeah, pretty much everything can ache, ache.
Okay. So our next word, x-ray, x-ray, x-ray,
x-hiffin, R-A-Y. Okay, pretty easy word.
So when you go to the doctor,
many times you'll get an x-ray.
It is a picture of
your bones. Right.
So that's an x-ray. All right, well,
we're going to hear both of these
words in the dialogue. So why don't
we listen as Gary visits his dentist?
Hey, Gary. Great
to see you again.
Please have a seat. So tell me
what seems to be the problem.
Thanks, Doc. I've got a really
bad toothache. I can't eat anything
and look, my face is all swollen. I
think it might be my wisdom teeth.
Well, let's have a look. Open
wide. This doesn't look good.
Well, it looks like you have a
cavity and your crown is loose.
So we'll need to put in a
filling before it gets any worse.
And the crown probably
needs to be refitted.
I'm going to order some
x-rays. Is it going to hurt?
No, not at all. Just
lay back and relax.
Okay, spit. Okay,
that always happens.
The dentist says no, it's not
going to hurt. Don't worry about it.
But it always hurts much more than he
says. Exactly. So in this dialogue, we saw
some interesting words when the dentist
was describing what problems Gary had.
Yes. So why don't we look at those now
in language takeaway? Language takeaway.
All right, let's take a look at our
first word. So Gary said that his face
was all swollen swollen swollen. So
swollen is an adjective, right, Marco?
Right. So his face is or was swollen. It
was bigger. Yeah, his face was bigger than
normal. Yes. Often when you hurt yourself,
that part of your body becomes swollen.
So you have to put some ice on it
usually and then the swelling will go down.
And that's the noun, the swelling. Right.
The swelling. And well, the verb to swell.
All right, three words for the
price of wine. So let's listen to
some examples of how we would
use the swelling swollen and to swell.
Example one. My nose is swollen.
It's the size of a football.
Example two. Put some ice on your
foot and the swelling will go down.
Example three. I got bitten by a
spider and my hand is swelling up.
All right, so Gary's face was swollen and he thought that it
was his wisdom teeth wisdom teeth. Okay, so this is interesting.
Wisdom is like wise. Yeah, knowledge knowledge. So these teeth,
they're not knowledgeable, but they're called wisdom teeth.
They're the teeth that grow last in your
mouth, right? Right. They are the last teeth
at the very end of your mouth. Yes, and
usually you get them when you're about 20.
And since they come out at this age, sometimes they interfere. They
hurt a little bit. So you have to get them taken out. Yes. All right,
wisdom teeth wisdom teeth. Okay. Now for our next word and something
that we all got as children cavity cavity, a cavity, a cavity.
It's a hole in your tooth. A hole in your tooth and it's
caused by too much sugar. Too much sugar, right? Or not
brushing your teeth enough. Yeah. So that's why everyone
had it. I think as children cavities. I never had a cavity.
Really? Yeah. Wow. Didn't have much sugar. I guess I was
a bit of a health nut when I was a kid. No, I wasn't.
My mom was. No, I guess not. All right, but enough about
my eating habits. Let's talk about our next word crown.
A crown. So a crown. This is interesting. We're not talking kings and greed. Right. That's the
first thing that comes to mind, right? Yeah. No, a crown is actually the visible part of your teeth.
Okay. So there's one part of your tooth that's inside that you can't see, right? That's called the
root. Yes. So when he said your crown is loose. What's he talking really about the actual tooth?
So sometimes people will lose a tooth or have a
really bad cavity. So the dentist needs to make a new
crown or a new visible part of the tooth for you. So
sometimes it'll be made of gold. Yep. Or porcelain.
Yeah. Exactly. So a crown. It's like a
really, really, really big filling. Mm-hmm.
Yeah. Crown. So his crown needed to
be refitted or put back into place. Yes.
Now our final word, uh, filling, filling
a filling. A filling. So I just said
this word previously. Mm-hmm. Now when
you have a cavity, you need to fill it in.
Right. You need to fill it with
something. Yes. Usually some sort of paste.
Uh-huh. And it gets really
hard. And just like your tooth.
Exactly. So then it covers up this cavity,
filling a filling. I have many fillings.
I wasn't very healthy as a kid.
All right, not a good toothbrush.
Sure. Exactly. So why don't we listen to
this dialogue again? And then we'll come
back and talk a little bit about some of the
interesting phrases that the doctor used.
Hey, Gary. Great
to see you again.
Please have a seat. So tell me
what seems to be the problem.
Thanks, Doc. I've got a really
bad toothache. I can't eat anything
and look, my face is all swollen. I
think it might be my wisdom teeth.
Well, let's have a look open wide. This doesn't
look good. Well, it looks like you have a
cavity and your crown is loose. We'll need
to put in a filling before it gets any worse.
And the crown probably needs to be
refitted. I'm going to order some x-rays.
Is it going to hurt? No, not
at all. Just lay back and relax.
Okay, spit.
Well, the dentist used three
really interesting phrases and I
want to look at the first one.
What seems to be the problem?
What seems to be the problem? Okay.
Very easy little sentence to ask
somebody what's wrong. Exactly. Right.
And I mean, these are small,
easy words, but when you put
them together, they sound
really natural and really fluent.
So if you ask somebody what
seems to be the problem is very
polite and it's a very good
way of asking what's wrong. Yes.
All right. Our next phrase
also made up of simple words.
Let's have a look. Let's
have a look. Let's have a look.
So this is a phrase that maybe your mechanic
or your dentist or your doctor will say
for anyone. Right. Let's have a look. Let's
look at it and see what the problem is.
Okay. Let's have a look.
Okay. And our final phrase.
It doesn't look good.
It doesn't look good. So I can
use this phrase for an object, right?
Yeah. Like this house
doesn't look good. Yes.
But here it's used a little bit
differently. So why don't we
listen to some examples to
help us understand the meaning?
Example one.
John told me it doesn't look good for me.
I probably won't get the job.
Example two.
It doesn't look good for Michael Jackson.
He's in a lot of debt.
Example three.
You know, the economy
doesn't look very good.
Okay. So in the examples, we can see that
they are using it for the situation. Yeah.
It looks maybe problematic. Yeah.
Yeah. So when you say
it doesn't look good, you
basically mean there
are going to be problems.
All right. It doesn't look good.
Yeah. Okay.
So great phrases, great words. Let's listen
to our Gary at the dentist one more time.
Then we'll come back
and talk a little bit more.
Hey, Gary. Great to see you again.
Please have a seat.
So tell me what seems to be the problem.
Things doc. I've got a really bad
toothache. I can't eat anything.
And look, my face is all swollen.
I think it might be my wisdom teeth.
Well, let's have a look open wide.
Oh, this doesn't look good.
Well, it looks like you have a
cavity and your crown is loose.
So we'll need to put in a
filling before it gets any worse.
And the crown probably
needs to be refitted.
I'm going to order some x-rays.
Is it going to hurt? No, not at all.
Just lay back and relax.
Wow.
Okay, spit.
Well, Marco, speaking of
dentists, have you ever had an
experience like this where you
spat out a tooth at the dentist?
Well, nothing so serious
as this, but actually, recently
when I was in Cambodia, all
right, you called us in Cambodia.
Well, our taxi driver
offered us to have some local
food and he said, well,
we're going to have a dog.
So that was interesting. Actually,
it wasn't that bad. It was pretty
good, but, you know, if you
get around the fact that it's a dog.
So what does this have
to do with your teeth?
I was eating it and I bit a bone that
was hidden and I chipped my tooth.
So you broke part of your tooth?
Yeah, like half of it, which I
had already chipped before.
So I had to go to the dentist
and so the dentist created a new
crown with not with gold or
porcelain, actually with a paste.
Oh, and then it becomes
hard and it just looks normal.
It doesn't even look like I
have a fake crown, so to say.
But dentists can be really expensive.
So how much did this cost?
Well, well, this was for
the bargain price of $10.
$10. That's how much it cost.
So we should all go to
Cambodia for dentistry.
Yeah, because actually it was pretty good.
He looked really young though. I was
kind of scared because when he walked
in, he looked like he was 19, but I
asked him his agent. He was like 30.
Okay, well, you're very trusting.
Yeah, so I imagine that you guys
maybe have some dental experiences,
so why don't you come to our
website and tell us all about it?
Yeah, visit us at
EnglishPod.com and you can find
lots more resources for
learning English there.
Well, guys, thanks for listening
and until next time. Bye-bye.